<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A proclamation or proscription, set foorth &amp; published by the archduke Albertus, against his mutinous soldiers in the castle of Hoochstrate. Printed at Bruxels. Faithfully translated into English out of the Dutch coppy printed at Middleborough, by the first originall.  Wherein is also truely set foorth the order of the two campes, before the stronge towne of Graue:  with the yeelding thereof into the hands of his Excellency Graue maurice: and the conditions agreed vpon both sides, the 19. of September.  Stilo nouo.  1602.  With other accidents since hapned.</title>
            <author>South Holland (Netherlands). Provinciale Staten.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1602</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 24 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08109</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18471</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100050</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99835903</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99835903</idno>
            <idno type="VID">134</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08109)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 134)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1282:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A proclamation or proscription, set foorth &amp; published by the archduke Albertus, against his mutinous soldiers in the castle of Hoochstrate. Printed at Bruxels. Faithfully translated into English out of the Dutch coppy printed at Middleborough, by the first originall.  Wherein is also truely set foorth the order of the two campes, before the stronge towne of Graue:  with the yeelding thereof into the hands of his Excellency Graue maurice: and the conditions agreed vpon both sides, the 19. of September.  Stilo nouo.  1602.  With other accidents since hapned.</title>
                  <author>South Holland (Netherlands). Provinciale Staten.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by E. Allde and R. Read] for Thomas Pauier, and are to bee solde at his shop in Corne-hill, at the signe of the Cat and two Parrets, neere the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1602.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: *4 A4 B1 (*1 possibly blank, lacking).</note>
                  <note>Printers from STC.</note>
                  <note>"Quire B printed by Read; the rest by Allde."--STC.</note>
                  <note>Pages 13-14 misnumbered 5-6.</note>
                  <note>Translated from the original Dutch.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of independence, 1556-1658 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Joe Kilduff</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Joe Kilduff</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:134:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:134:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Proclamation or Proſcription, ſet foorth &amp; pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished by the Arch-duke Albertus, againſt his Mutinous Soldiers in the Caſtle of <hi>Hoochſtrate.</hi> Printed at <hi>Bruxels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Faithfully tranſlated into English out of the Dutch Coppy Printed at Middleborough, by the firſt Originall.</p>
            <p>Wherein is alſo truely ſet foorth the order of the two Campes, before the ſtronge towne of Graue: With the yeelding thereof into the hands of his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency Graue Maurice: and the conditions agreed vpon on both ſides, the 19. of Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. Stilo Nouo. 1602.</p>
            <p>With other accidents ſince hapned.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for Thomas Pauier, and are to bee ſolde at his ſhop in Corne-hill, at the ſigne of the Cat and two Parrets, neere the Royall Exchange. 1602.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:134:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:134:2"/>
            <head>A Proclamation, publiſhed and ſet foorth at Bruxelles, by the Arch-duke <hi>Albertus</hi> and the Dutches, againſt their Mutinous Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers lying in the Caſtile of Hoochſtrate.</head>
            <opener>
               <signed>The Arch-duke and Dutcheſſe.</signed>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>EE hauing aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled our boaſt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> town of <hi>Graue,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiedges by our enemies where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers of the ſaid Towne do valiantly defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning great praiſe and honour: And our ſelues in perſon en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuouring
<pb facs="tcp:134:3"/>to aduaunce the buſineſſe: vnderſtand, that ſome of the Soldiers of our foreſaid Camp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (which was approached very néere vnto the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies forces) vnder colour of deſire to Mutiny, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to obtaine that which they falſly pretended to be due vnto them, haue in moſt villanous order, left and forſaken their Auncientes and Cullours, and after many attempts on ſundry places, haue by villanous and Traytorous meanes taken the Caſtle of <hi>Hoochſtrate:</hi> giuing to vnderſtand by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and waighty argumentes, that they deale and holde coreſpondent with our enemies, and that by them they will help themſelues, which by all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and lawes is forbidden, and neuer before v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed or practiſed by any other Soldiers. But con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe, ſuch as haue héertofore mutined (at ſuch times as the enemy beſiedged any of our Townes, or if wee had any occaſion to vſe Soldiers for our warres) they came out of ſuch places as they poſſeſſed, ſeruing vs with great zeale and obedience. And for as much as the principalleſt ring-leaders of this treaſon &amp; villanous acte, are ſuch perſons to whom nothing, or very litle is owing, being partly but of late entertained, and partly ſuch as were in the alterations in <hi>Deeſt, Weert</hi> and <hi>Karpen,</hi> where they receiued their count &amp; reckoning for as much as was owing vnto them: yea, &amp; are ſuch people as are accuſtomed to raiſe Mutinies, by which meanes they might inioy ſuch ſummes of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney as procéede of the contributions, without doing any ſeruice vnto vs: and alſo haue delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, forced, and animated others to effect this Trayterous action, whereby wee are hindred from effecting the reſcue of their beſiedged fellows (in armes) and bretheren: and alſo from all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:134:3"/>exploytes which we might accompliſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> our enemyes, binding vs by theſe their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ings to turne our ſwoord againſt them, as againſt our owne and ciuill enemies: yea, and are more hurtfull then they, in ſo much as the enemyes force is thereby greatly increaſed. For as much therefore that this their action is newe, the like before not heard of, vilde, vnſéemely, and of ill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, and deſerueth exemplarily to be puniſhed: So it is therefore, that wee deſtring to foreſée ſome wholeſome remedie for the common profit, and welfare of our vaſſailes and ſubiectes: doe ordaine and commaund all our Soldiers and other perſons of their company, being in the Caſtle of <hi>Hoochſtrate,</hi> eyther there or elſe where, in any other place aſſembled vnder colour or pretext of Mutiny, that within thrée daies after the publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion héereof, they returne to their Auncients and Cullours, or doe preſent themſelues vnto the Gouernours of <hi>Leere</hi> or of <hi>Herentacls</hi> to be ſent vnto their Cullours or Auncients, where they ſhal be quietly and ioyfully receiued, as if this alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on had not hapned: promiſing them in the word and faith of a Prince, that neither now, nor héer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after they ſhall not for this offence receiue any puniſhment, nor bee farther examined, no not though they be of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chiefeſt &amp; principalleſt actors of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid mutiny, but ſhal be vſed fauourably &amp; louing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, rendring vnto them al curteſie, as vnto ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, to whom we wiſh all good. And if it ſo fall out that they accompliſhe not this our fauourable wil &amp; pleaſure (the aforeſaid <hi>3.</hi> dates being expired) we haue from hence forth declared all thoſe which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently remain w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them, as alſo al others w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> héerafter
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:134:4"/>ſhal ioyne with them, and by theſe Preſents doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare and pronounce for Rebels, Traitors wicked villaines and miſchieuous perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, as hauing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted <hi>crimen lezae Maieſtatis</hi> in the higheſt degrée. and for ſuch Rebels and Traitors condemne them to death, and their goods to be forfeited: which we will and commaund to be written vp, and brought into our Treaſury of Demaines or profit. Giu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lycenſe vnto all and euery perſon of what qual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, ſtate or condicion ſoeuer they bee, freely and without any daunger of Lawe, to kill the ſayd Muniters, without reſpect of any perſon, whether the ſame bee done priuily, ſodenly, or otherwiſe howſoeuer, and as the ſame may bee found moſt eaſily, and by the beſt meanes to be effected. And whoſoeuer ſhall performe this our pleaſure, and kill any of theſe Mutiners, ſhall receiueten crowns or euery head: and for euery head of ſuch as haue béen ordenary Officers, <hi>100.</hi> Crownes: And for the heades of ſuch others as they terme by the names of Councellers, Sergeant-Maior, Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Cauallery, &amp;c. two hundreth crownes, and for their Electo fiue hundred Crownes. And if ſo bee that any of their owne company, ſhall murder or kill any of them, wee pardon his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and will cauſe the aforeſaid ſummes to bee paide him. Furthermore, we ordaine &amp; command, all Iudges and Iuſtices of our Campes, townes &amp; countryes, to inuentary and take notice in writing, of all the goods (as wel mooueable as inmooueable) belonging vnto the ſaid Mutiners, and what perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly appertaineth to euery one: And alſo of their apparrell, and of any other like thing whatſoeuer, belonging vnto their wiues and children all which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:134:4"/>our pleaſure is, ſhall be deliuered into the handes of our depoſetarie Officers of our Campe, and a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificate thereof to bee ſent to the Superintendent Iuſticer of our ſaid Campe, to the ende that all the ſame may bee brought into our Treaſury of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines, whether we appoint the ſame from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foorth to be brought. nd further, wee charge and commaund all and euery perſon whatſoeuer, which ſhall haue any money or other thinges belonging to the forenamed Mutiners, or to their Wiues or children, laide to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to gage, deliuered by exchange, in <hi>Depoſito,</hi> or to be kept, in what maner ſoeuer it be, that they deliuer not the ſame vnto them, but that they open and make known the ſame vnto vs, that the ſame may bee confiſcated as is before ſaid, on paine to forfeit all their goods if any ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale the ſame: and further, to receiue iudiciall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. And for as much as the deformity of the offence, and wicked conſequence that might therof enſue to other Princes, vnto whom the ſame might (in time to come) happen in their Campes, if ſuch wicked beginnings and practiſes ſhould not be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed: Wee ſolicite and deſire the Emperour and King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> our Lords and bretheren, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Kings, Princes, &amp; Potentates, in what places or lands the ſaid Mutiners ſhal be found, or haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny goods, that they will commaund the ſame to bee arreſted, ſending them vnto vs with the aforeſaid certificates accordingly, and to the end as is before ſet downe: and we will be willing at their requeſt, to accompliſh the ſame in our Landes &amp; Lordſhips, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tall times when they ſhall requeſt the ſame of vs. Likewiſe we prohibit and forbid the ſaid wiues, children of the Mutiners, to goe vnto the place &amp;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:134:5"/>where the ſaid Mutiners are, commaunding them not to deale nor meddle with them, either by word or writting, ſo long as the ſaid alteration ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, on paine of death: permitting all perſons whatſoeuer to apprehend and ſpotle them, which ſhal not be reckoned for any offence, if ſo be they go, or that there be any ſuſpicion that they deſire to goe vnto their ſaid fathers or huſbandes: but wee will and commaund, that within throe daies they depart out of our countries, and not to returne without our caue and liſence firſt had, on paine as is before ſaid, Alſo wée commaund, that no man (eyther within our land or wout) vnder colour or pretext of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, victulers, ſeruants or otherwiſe, ſhall do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſeruice. aſſiſt, or carry any victuals, munition or other things, vnto the ſaid mutiners, nor vnto their boyes, ſeruantes, or horſes, or any thing or thinges that concerneth them, no not for their money, on paine of death, and other fines ccording to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation of our Iudges, weightineſſe of the cauſe, and quality of the perſons: Giuing alſo our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, that it ſhall bee lawfull to kill them, without offence to our lawes, if ſo be they ſhall be found <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flagranti.</hi> And further we will and commaund that the proper names and ſurnames, ſhall be taken out of the Bookes and Regiſters of the Pay-maſters of our ſaid Campe, with their markes, and places where the ſaid changelings or mutiners, &amp; parents were borne: and it more apparant euidence ſhall ſéeme needfull, we will and commaund that due in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation be taken, that it may manifeſtly be ſéene what they be that are condemned: and that the ſaid changelings ſhal be proclaymed in our Palace, and in the places where they are borne and inhabite (as
<pb facs="tcp:134:5"/>well in theſe our Counties, as in the Dominions of the Emperour or the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and other Princes our friendes and confederates) for wicked villaines, traytors &amp; vnprofitable perſons, hauing committed <hi>Crimen lezae Maieſtatis in primo caſu.</hi> And further more, we will and commaund, to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute againſt them, their children and ſucceſſors, the forfeitures and penalties by lawes prouided for all ſuch perſons, whereof from hence forward, we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce them to be fallen into, and to be condemn-(e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e ndall ſuch as ſhall becauſe of the ſuppreſſion of this mutinous rebellion, and deliuer into our hands, ſuch as are offendors therein, wee forgiue them. and offer to giue them an honourable recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence: and alſo vnto all ſuch as ſhall be ayders and aſſiſtantes therein, although they bee of the ſame mutinous company, and chéefeſt ring-leaders or Officers amongſt them. And to the ende that this our preſent Proclamation and preſcription, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out infringement, may be holden and kept, and that all men may take knowledge thereof, as well the Generall of the light horſemen, the Captaine of the handes of Ordinance, Maſter of the Artilerie, Collonels, Marſhals, Gouernours, heads, Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines and Commaunders, Soldiers and all other men of warre, of what ſtate, condition, quallity, or nation ſoeuer they be: as alſo al others our vaſſalls and ſubiectes: we will and commaund that the ſame be publiſhed as a publique baniſhment, and coppy attentique thereof be ſent vnto the lycentiate <hi>Iohn de Frias,</hi> Councellor to the Kings Maieſty, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perintendent of Iuſtice in the campe in theſe quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, that he may put the ſame in execution accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly, and to be obſerued eyther in part or whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb facs="tcp:134:6"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Generall, and to other Officers and perſons, vnto whom it ſhall appertaine, that all places of Iuſtice as well of townes as villages, may be aduertiſed of the iſſue thereof, and himſelfe to impart vnto vs the proceedinged héerein, that farther inſight may be had, and ſuch order preſcribed as ſhall be néedful for the execution and vpright ordering of all mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters before ſpeciſied. And like wiſe wee will and commaund, that an attentique Coppy ſhall be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered vnto Sir <hi>Iohn Richarddot</hi> Knight, and high Preſident of our Priuy and Secret Councell, and of the Councell of our Councell of State, to the end that he alſo (ſo farre as the ſame both concerne him) cauſe this our ordinance to bee followed and kept, and to commaund in our name, all Iudges and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of our countries in theſe parts, likewiſe to performe the ſame.</p>
            <p>In witnes whereof wee haue cauſed theſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents to be dilligently diſpatched, and our Seale thereon hanged.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen at <hi>Deeſt</hi> 
                  <date>the <hi>15.</hi> day of September, in the yeere of our Lord. <hi>1602.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Vnder witten. <hi>Albert.</hi> And ſomewhat lower. At the ordinance of their Highnes. And ſubſcribed. <hi>I. de Mancicidor.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="description">
            <pb facs="tcp:134:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The deſcription of the two Campes,</hi> lying before the ſtrong towne of Graue, beſiedged by the Noble Prince Graue Maurice.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſtrong towne of <hi>Graue,</hi> in the land of <hi>Cuycke,</hi> lying on the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of <hi>Maſe,</hi> is in compaſſe, as great as a man can goe about in halfe an houre, belonging to my Lord the Prince of <hi>Orenge,</hi> and hath of long time remained in the poſſeſſion of the Spaniards. This yéere <hi>1602.</hi> the <hi>18.</hi> day of Auguſt, his Excellency <hi>Graue Maurice</hi> of <hi>Naſſau</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſledged this towne, and the next day following, layde a bridge ouer the <hi>Maſe:</hi> they of the towne (liſle doubting any ſuch matter) were (according to the trueſt intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence) not aboue <hi>1500.</hi> Soldiers, and about ſome <hi>300.</hi> Towneſ-men or Burgers, not very well prouided of victuals and Muni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion: Notwithſtanding, the towne is ſtrengly Manited with Bulwarkes, Walles and Ditches, for the laſt yéere they ioyned to their Walles ſuch Bulwarkes as were ſeperated from the Towne with a ditch, for theyr greater ſtrength. They loſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a Fort which lay on the other ſide of the <hi>Maſe,</hi> called <hi>Vaine coſt</hi> or <hi>Loſt charges:</hi> which in truth was of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſmall force or ſtrength. Moreouer (as ſoone as his
<pb facs="tcp:134:7"/>Excellency approached the towne (they made a Trench round about the Towne, ſtrengthned with certaine poyntes. His Excellency preſently made a Batterie, right againſt the ſaide Fort, called <hi>Loſt charges</hi> vppon the Cauſey, and Battered it with the Cannon: whereupon the Enemie forſooke it in the night time, and his Excellencie hauing poſſeſſion thereof, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently rayſed a Mount, and planted ſeauen peeces of Ordinaunce thereon. At the beginning they of the Towne kept themſelues very quiet, ſhooting little, but made (euery night in a manner) ſignes and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens by fire, which they ſtill continue to doe. His Excellencie knowing very well that the Enemie (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the fieldes) would viſit him, did in an incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſtrong manner, intrench himſelfe againſt his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, for hee made all his workes high and with thicke walles. Flancking one vpon the other, and are all doubled, and many three double, with a wide Ditch round about, and in many places high Batte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. Beſides theſe fortifications, hee hath round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him (without the Campe) about foureteene Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duites, wherein Guard is kept, which lye a Muſket ſhot from the vttermoſt Trenches, euery one garded with <hi>50.</hi> Muſket ſhot continually.</p>
            <p>The order of our Campe is thus, beginning with his Excellencies Quarter, which lyeth vpwardes the Maze beyond the Towne, where hee hath placed two Shippe bridges ouer the Riuer, and a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond them are two Iron chaynes, to hinder the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of the Enemies Shippes of Fire worke: At this place his Excellency hath rayſed ſundry high bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, to withſtand the Enemies approach behinde him, and towards the towne hée hath very ſtrong Reduites made on the Cauſey for his defence. In this his Excellencies Quarter, where alſo the <hi>Graue</hi> of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:134:7"/>
               <hi>Hollocke</hi> lyeth) lye moſt of the Caualery, with the French and Duch Soldiers: The outward part of theſe workes lye halfe an houres goeing from the Walles of the Towne. The ſecond Quarter of <hi>Graue William</hi> ioyneth vnto this of his Exellencyes, ſtretching towards the higheſt of the Heath, where his Honor lyeth intrenched vpon the high grounds, with diuers Forts ond Batteries, and it is a long halfe houres goeing from the walles of the Towne, to the furtheſt part of theſe workes: in this Quarter lye the Vreeſes, Scottes, and other Soldiers. The third Quarter is Sir <hi>Francis Veares,</hi> lyncked hard vnto this other of Earle <hi>Williams,</hi> reaching foorth downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward towards the Towne euen vnto the riuer of the Maze, where hee hath alſo the Cauſie or ditch to his aduantage: heere the Engliſhmen lye, and haue a bridge alſo made of Shippes, where mightie ſtore of Shippes lye furniſhed with Victuals and Munition, and is the place where the Market is kept. Againſt the Towne beyond the Maze is no ſpeciall Quarter kept, but that the Soldiers as well of the Caualery as of the Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery come thether ouer the Bridge to guard the ſame.</p>
            <p>On this ſide, the Ditch or Cauſey ſerueth his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency for a ſtrong Trench, whereon hee hath made ſundrye Reduites. Alſo hee hath heere made an high battery, (as before is written) from whence with his ſhot hee may mightilie annoy the Towne, which towards this place declineth and lyeth lowe: and from this place hath Fire workes been ſundrye times ſhot into the Towne. The circuite of the Campe from the Engliſh Quarter vnto the Maze in his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies Quarter, will aſke aboue fiue houres go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>Now when the Enemie had aſſembled his Troopes,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:134:8"/>and had remained ſome fewe dayes in the land of <hi>Claue:</hi> the <hi>10.</hi> of Auguſt hee came marching by fayre day light, euen within halfe an houres going to his Excellencyes Quarter, where he pitched his Tentes, and made a Ship bridge ouer the Maze. They of the towne beholding this, made great ioy, and triumphed with their ſhot: and the ſaid day, ſallyed twiſe out of the towne, on the Quarters of the Vréeſes, and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther daies afterwards alſo, but to their ſmall profit.</p>
            <p>His Excellency hath alſo greatly approached the Towne with running Trenches out of his Quarter, along the edge of the Maze, where it is high, and hath brought the ſame euen to the Enemies Trenches: The like is done from <hi>Graue Williams</hi> Quarter, and from Sir <hi>Frances Veares</hi> Quarter, along the ſide of the Maze, and are all come euen to the Enemies running Trenches.</p>
            <p>Alſo, his Excellency hath <hi>5.</hi> Batteries, from whence he ſhooteth againſt the Towne: one before the Maze, two in the Engliſh Quarter ſtanding vpon the Ditch, and two on the land ſide.</p>
            <p>Betwéene the <hi>12.</hi> and <hi>13.</hi> of uguſt, about <hi>12.</hi> of the clocke in the night, they of the Towne began won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully to ſhoote, from all Quarters till morning, and thereupon made a ſhoute, and forcecible ſallye with ſixe hundred men vpon the Vreeſes Quarter, but more luſtily reſiſted and driuen into the Towne, leauing many of their men dead behinde them: At the ſame in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant the Enemy behinde alſo began to approach both with horſe and foote: but after he found himſelfe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noyed with our Ordinaunce, he wiſely turned backe again: The ſame night was aworthy Captaine of ours (one of his Excellencies Inieners) ſhot in the Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, called <hi>Andreas de Roy.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:134:8"/>
            <p>As Sir <hi>Francis Veare</hi> was giuing order which way the Trenches ſhould be brought, he was ſtrocke in the face with a ſmall bullet, which remayneth in his necke, the wound is (God be thanked) healed though it ſéemed more dangerous at the firſt.</p>
            <p>The <hi>15.</hi> of Auguſt (being our Lady day) they thought to effect ſome great matter, the ſame day at one of the clocke in the afternoone they ſalied out with great force vpon the Engliſh quarter, forcing themſelues with ſome <hi>700.</hi> men to breake thorow, but they were ſtoutly repul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he fight continuing almoſt an houre long but in the end, the en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>my was glad to turne his backe, among whome many were ſlaine with our ordinance, which played vpon them from diuers places. In this ſally there were Cap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aynes ſlayne on both ſides, with ſome hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of the enimies ſouldiers. The ſame time the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my marched towards our Campe, but came n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t verye neare, yet ſhewing themſelues in ample order of battaile amongſt the trées right ouer againſt his Excellencies quarter, but (after he had ſtayed the diſcharging of ſome great ſhot from our Campe) he turned back: And this was the greateſt and fierceſt ſally that yet hapned ſince the beſiedging of the Towne.</p>
            <p>Concerning the enemies Campe, the ſame remayned there vntill the <hi>22.</hi> day of this moneth of Auguſt, now and then ſhewing himſelfe: and many ſkirmidges hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned betwéene them, and thoſe which kept the watches without the Campe, but neuer made attempt with any great force, which our people would gladly haue ſéene, as well the meaneſt as the chiefeſt.</p>
            <p>There ran very many from the enemies dayly, which came vnto our Camp, declaring that they were forced ſo to do by extremity of hunger, that great dearth and pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nury was in their Campe, and that they had no money, ſo that it was impoſſible for the Admirant to lye long in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:134:9"/>that place, affirming farther, that if the reſt of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, had but confidence of like fauour to be ſhowen by his Excellency, as he had ſhowen vnto them, very few would remaine with the Admirant, yet his Excellency ſuffereth not any to remayne in his Campe, but giueth them paſport to depart.</p>
            <p>The <hi>22.</hi> day of Auguſt in the euening about <hi>10.</hi> of the clock the great Admirant with his mighty campe brake vp, hauing ſent away his waggons and baggage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him and followed with all his forces as ſecretly as he could, without ſounding of trumpet or drum. His Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency being hereof aduertiſed, early in the morning followed him, with <hi>4000.</hi> horſemen, and <hi>1200.</hi> Muſket<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>téeres, but they were too farre paſſed: Thus the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant with his great campe departed, leauing his friends in their greateſt extremity, and the towne of <hi>Graue</hi> to his Excellency for a pray.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:134:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
